Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Thompson, Abraham Rand, 1781-1866. Letter, 1833, June 7, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Massachusetts physician. Letter (ALS). Thompson refers to President Andrew Jackson's visit to the Bunker Hill monument in Boston and describes Commodore Jesse D. Elliott, the commander of the Charleston Navy Yard.
  - Thompson, Henry, Sir, 1820-1904. Papers, 1864-1874, (2 items) (Box 12)
    British surgeon. Note (ANS), a dinner invitation, and a letter (ALS), advocating the adoption of the practice of cremation. Items are accompanied by a bibliographic note describing Thompson's dinner parties.
  - Thouret, Michel-Augustin, 1748 or 9-1810. Note, 1798, Sept. 30, (1 item) (Box 12)
    French physician. Note requesting that addressee communicate information regarding veterinary schools directly to Lieut. Cabanis.
  - Throop, Amos, 1738-1814. Letter, 1807, Nov. 4, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Pioneer, philanthropist and founder of Throop University, later the California Institute of Technology. Letter (ALS) to his nephew, then a student at Phillips Exeter Academy. Throop praises the academic reputation of the school, relates news of a cotton mill fire and reports on the health of various family members.
  - Ticknor, Luther, 1790-1846. Papers, 1824-1847, (13 items) (Box 12)
    Physician of Salisbury, Conn. Accounts of expenses incurred by the town of Salisbury and by various inhabitants against Dr. Luther Ticknor. Papers also include Adam Reid's Discourse delivered at the funeral of Luther Ticknor.
  - Tiedemann, Friedrich, 1781-1861. Note, [Between 1816 and 1848], (1 item) (Box 12)
    German anatomist and physiologist. Note (ANS). Requests a meeting with recipient.
  - Tiemann, George. Document, 1834, Aug. 26, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Patent granted to Tiemann for a surgical instrument called the scarificator. Consists of a form statement, signed by President Andrew Jackson; three drawings of the instrument; and specifications regarding the instrument, written and signed by Tiemann. Patent issued in 1834 and renewed in 1846.
  - Tilton, James, 1745-1822. Letter, 1815, Dec. 6, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Army surgeon and politician. Letter (ALS). Informs Dr. Perlee that his, Tilton's, leg must be amputated and summons him to perform the operation.
  - Torrey, John, 1796-1873. Papers, 1818-1859, (59 items) (Box 12)
    U.S. physician and botanist. Papers consist mostly of letters written to Torrey by professional colleagues, botanists and geologists involved in exploration and surveyor expeditions. Notable correspondents include Louis Agassiz, A. D. Bache, Spencer Fullerton Baird, George Bentham, Jacob Bigelow, James Dwight Dana, William Darlington, Amos Eaton, Ebenezer Emmons, Asa Gray, A. Guyot, Robert Hare, Joseph Henry, Edward Hitchcock, John Lindley, Josiah Clark Nott, C. S. Rafinesque, and John White Webster. A complete list of correspondents is available.
  - Tracy, Elisha, b. 1712. Document, 1778, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Physician. Holograph document. Statement of payment due from Major Joshua Huntington for medical services for the years 1776-1778.
  - Treat, Malachi. Letter, 1780, Aug. 22, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Physician-General of the Northern Division of the Medical Department of the Continental Army during the Revolutionary War. Letter (ALS). Treat requests medical supplies and reports of Indian atrocities on the frontier.
  - Treves, Frederick, Sir, 1853-1923. Letter, 1902, Feb. 18, (1 item) (Box 12)
    British surgeon. Letter (ALS). Informs Talbot that upon his return to London he will suggest the appointment of a subcommittee to report upon a certain matter.
  - Trousseau, Armand, 1801-1867. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 12)
    French clinician. Letter (ALS). Asks Collard to befriend a St. Marc, who seeks reinstatement to his former position as principal of a college.
  - Tuke, Daniel Hack, 1827-1895. Papers, undated, (2 items) (Box 12)
    English psychiatrist. Autograph manuscripts, signed. Two sonnets, on his mother's miniature and on the burial of his son, April 20, 1883.
  - Turk, William. Letter, 1854, Sept. 24, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Naval surgeon. Letter (ALS). In this letter written two months before his death on Nov. 20, 1854, Turk writes of attending "the Lectures" in Philadelphia, recounts youthful escapades and speaks of his family.
  - Turner, Dawson, 1775-1858. Papers, 1800-1820, (3 items) (Box 12)
    English physician and botanist. Letters (ALS) from naturalist James de Carl Sowerby and from the founder of the Linnean Society, Sir James Edward Smith, on botany.
  - Turner, Edward Kitchen. Letter, 1777, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Physician. Letter (ALS). Requests funds to purchase instruments and supplies, including blankets, bandage linen and a tourniquet, to be used in military service.
  - Turner, Peter. Papers, 1773-1792, (4 items) (Box 12)
    Physician. Holograph document, signed by Fre. Smythe, is a New Jersey medical license. Note (ANS) documents his finding that a William Young is fit for mustering, an IOU, and the receipt of dividends from shares in the Ohio Company.
  - Turner, W. Papers, 1827 and undated, (2 items) (Box 12)
    Rhode Island physician. Letter (ALS). Turner appeals to Major Milo Mason and to William Hunter for help in unspecified matters.
  - Turner, William. Letter, 1802, Sept. 18, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Surgeon. Letter (ALS). A copy of his letter to Miss "Fanny" Clifton, written hours before his departure to the Mediterranean for Naval service, in which he passionately bids her farewell.
  - Tweedale, John. Letter, 1831, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Physician. Letter (ALS). Proposal to erect a monument in honor of the passage of the Reform Bill.
  - Tyndall, John, 1820-1893. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Scientist and natural philosopher. Letter (ALS). Tyndall inquires after "the character of the instruction" received by the two sons of a deceased acquaintance.
  - Vaihinger, Hans, 1852-1933. Postcard, 1884, Nov. 16, (1 item) (Box 12)
    German psychologist and philosopher. Autograph postcard, signed. A biographical note accompanies card.
  - Vallisnieri, Antonio, 1661-1730. Letters, 1724-1729, (15 items) (Box 12)
    Italian physician and scientist. Consists of various letters (ALS) to and from Vallisnieri.
  - Vanderburgh, Federal, 1788-1868. Letter, 1850, Sept. 8, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Homeopathic physician. Letter (ALS). Prescribes a course of treatment for a child patient.
  - Vaughan, Benjamin, 1751-1835. Letter, 1807, Oct. 3, (1 item) (Box 12)
    English physician and solicitor, who moved to the U.S. after the French Revolution. Autograph letter, unsigned. Invites Judge Bowen to dine at his house during his stay in Stroudwater.
  - Vauquelin, Louis Nicolas, 1763-1829. Letter, 1805, Sept. 25 or 26, (1 item) (Box 12)
    French chemist and neurochemist. Letter (ALS). Recommends a M. Gallet for a position of copy clerk.
  - Verneuil, A. A. (Aristide Auguste Stanislas), 1823-1895. Letters, 1884 and undated, (4 items) (Box 12)
    French surgeon. Letters (ALS). Correspondents include: M. Letulle and M. Palla. Discusses patients and a conference presided over by V. Cornil.
  - Verney, Pierre, 1650-1728. Manuscript, 1723, Jan. 13, (1 item) (Box 12)
    French anatomist, member of the faculty of medicine at Montpellier. Manuscript (AMS). Prescribes course for treatment, including purging and a milk diet, for a case involving respiratory and digestive disorders.
  - Verral, Charles. Letter, [1800s?], (1 item) (Box 12)
    Letter (ALS). Sends a copy of his latest work.
  - Verworn, Max, 1863-1921. Letter, 1912, Jan. 8, (1 item) (Box 12)
    German physiologist. Letter (ALS). Sends copies of a lecture to a colleague in Baltimore.
  - Vincent, Swale, 1868-1933. Autograph card, 1919, Oct. 17, (1 item) (Box 12)
    Card signed by Swale Vincent, 17-10-1919.
  - Virchow, Rudolf, 1821-1902. Papers, 1865-1874, (2 items) (Box 12)
    German pathologist. Letters (ALS). Writes a note of thanks and sends instructions to his publisher.
  - Voelcker, Friedrich, b. 1872. Letter, 1924, Oct. 18, (1 item) (Box 12)
    German urologist. Letter (TLS). Reports that a manuscript will be ready on April 1, 1925.
  - Vulpian, Alfred, 1826-1887. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 13)
    French physiologist. Letter (ALS). Writes regarding the editing of a publication on Parkinson's disease.
  - Wadd, William, 1776-1829. Letter, 1823, Feb. 15, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS). Inquires whether addressee possesses the proof impression of a portrait.
  - Walker, Mary Edwards, 1832-1919. Papers, 1885-1898, (2 items) (Box 13)
    Suffrage activist and pioneer female surgeon. Letters (ALS). Walker writes to a Daniel P. Farrington, regarding her actions to secure voting rights for women, and to a Ralph Greenbaum, expressing her desire to build a hospital, home and school for tuberculosis patients.
  - Ward, Humphry, Mrs., 1851-1920. Letter, 1915, Dec. 7, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English novelist and social worker. Letter (ALS). A social letter.
  - Wardrop, James, 1782-1869. Letter, 1813, Nov. 5, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English surgeon and ophthalmologist. Letter (ALS). Writes to his publisher concerning the second volume of his work, Morbid Anatomy of the Human Eye.
  - Ware, John, 1795-1864. Letter, 1835, June 9, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Physician and ophthalmic surgeon of Massachusetts. Letter (ALS). Reports no great change in the condition of a Miss Andrews and prescribes various medicines.
  - Warner, Mr. Document, [1861], (1 item) (Box 4)
    A record, possibly written by Warner, of the amount owed by Warner to Dr. Thomas Miner for services to himself to treat a case of syphilis.
  - Warren, John Collins, 1778-1856. Papers, 1825-1856, (12 items) (Box 13)
    Boston surgeon. Letters (ALS), including a description of the Siamese twins Chang and Eng, prescriptions and a letter of recommendation, and newspaper clippings of obituary notices.
  - Warren, Samuel, 1807-1877. Letter, 1840, July 27, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English physician and novelist. Letter (ALS). Declines an invitation and relates personal news.
  - Watts, Charles. Papers, 1813-1833, (6 items) (Box 13)
    Lawyer from New York, practiced in New Orleans. Letters (ALS) to his sister, Helen, and her husband, Henry F. Jones, in which he describes his legal career and life in New Orleans. He refers to epidemics of yellow fever and cholera and notes that the climate is considered to be beneficial to tuberculosis patients.
  - Webster, Benjamin. Papers, 1867, (3 items) (Box 13)
    Notes (ANS). A note and a prescription from surgeon Edwin Canton. A note for physician William Bell.
  - Webster, John White, 1793-1850. Letter, 1845, Sept. 24, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Professor of chemistry at Harvard University. Letter (ALS). Instructions for the forwarding of some books and for the purchase of a map of the Hudson River.
  - Weigert, Carl, 1845-1904. Postcard, 1897, Feb. 9, (1 item) (Box 13)
    German biochemist. Postcard, signed. Writes regarding a recently published article by Ehrlich.
  - Weitzel, John. Document, 1779, Jan., (1 item) (Box 13)
    Physician. Holograph document, signed by Weitzel. Statement of amount due to physician John Weitzel for attendance and medicine to two wounded men at prison district 96 in South Carolina.
  - Welch, William Henry, 1850-1934. Correspondence, 1887-1933 and undated, (24 items) (Box 13)
    U.S. physician, scientist, and educator. A group of letters spanning Welch's career, chiefly written to him, but including one early 1887 letter returning a revised manuscript to Dr. Canfield. One notable letter introducing Welch, then at Johns Hopdkins, to Congressman Robert Bremner, is signed by Woodrow Wilson from the White House in 1913. Includes many pieces of correspondence to and from Wilburt C. Davison of the Duke University School of Medicine, including a 1933 telegram to Welch on the occasion of the 2nd anniversary.
  - Wells, Horace, 1815-1848. Papers, 1839-1860, (2 items) (Box 13)
    Dentist of Hartford, Conn. A copy of The Hartford Times (May 25, 1839), in which Wells advertised his dental practice. A letter from Wells' widow, Elizabeth Wells, regarding her husband's claim to be the discoverer of anesthesia.
  - Wheaton, Levi, 1761-1851. Papers, 1819-1851, (3 items) (Box 13)
    Physician of Providence, Rhode Island. A statement of charges accrued during the last illness of Col. Smith and clippings of obituary notices.
  - Wilde, William Robert, 1815-1876. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Irish physician, father of Oscar Wilde. Note (ANS). Accepts invitation.
  - Williams, David. Letter, 1823, May 17, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Letter (ALS). Inquires after a paper submitted for publication.
  - Willoughby, Westel Woodbury, 1867-1945. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Professor of obstetrics, College of Physician and Surgeons of the Western District, University of the State of New York. Letter (ALS) of recommendation for Doctor Forester Dexter.
  - Wilson, Erasmus, Sir, 1809-1884. Letters, 1847-1878, (3 items) (Box 13)
    English surgeon. Three letters (ALS). Pertains to the exchange of copies of a book by Wilson. Wilson asks for Hunt's marked copy and offers a fresh copy. Third unrelated letter.
  - Wintringham, Clifton, Sir, 1710-1794. Letter, 1793, Jan. 23, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English physician. Letter (ALS). Writes regarding the publication of the second volume of his work, Commentaries, with the firm of Cadell and Davies of London.
  - Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818. Papers, 1815-1839, (2 items) (Box 13)
    Physician and professor of anatomy. Papers include a receipt of payment for attendance by Wistar upon a Wm. Cohen, and an 1839 invitation card to a Wistar Party.
  - Wood, Horatio C., 1841-1920. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Philadelphia therapeutist. Letter (ALS). Refers the addressee to Alfred Stillé's and John Shaw Billings' writings on cholera.
  - Wood, William Maxwell, 1809-1880. Journal, 1849, Aug. 23, (1 item) (Box 13)
    U.S. naval surgeon. Autograph manuscript. Part of Wood's journal of a trip accompanying President Zachary Taylor.
  - Woodbridge, Dudley. Letter, 1770, Apr., (1 item) (Box 13)
    Physician of Groton, Conn. Letter (ALS). Woodbridge writes to his son concerning a land controversy involving the dower of Mrs. Mumford.
  - Woodville, William, 1752-1805. Document, 1800, May 10, (1 item) (Box 13)
    British physician. Autograph document, signed. A receipt of payment from Wm. Phillips.
  - Wyman, Walter, 1848-1911. Letter, 1909, Nov. 6, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Physician. Letter (TLS). Asks that the use of the club be extended to J. W. Babcock of Columbia, South Carolina.
  - Yeats, Grant David, 1773-1836. Document, 1817, Sept. 3, (1 item) (Box 13)
    English medical writer. A prescription, signed.
  - Zimmerman, Johann Georg, 1714-1795. Letter, 1784, June 27, (1 item) (Box 13)
    German physician. Letter (ALS). Describes the case history of Prince Frederick of England, who suffered from attacks of intermittent fever and convulsive asthma.
  - Zoological Society, London. Letter, between 1828 and 1841, (1 item) (Box 13)
    Letter (ALS)addressed to Zoological Society leaders from an Anna Maria Dawes, listing names of individuals in support of her proposal to the Society to offer "ices, confectionery &c." at the Society's Garden, which opened to members in 1828. Signed by 16 men, including Henry Halford, royal physician, scientist William Haseldine Pepys (related to a first cousin of Samuel Pepys), and physician George Birkbeck.